<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bogg-witticisms, or, Dear joy's common-places being a compleat collection of the most profound punns, learned bulls, elaborate quibbles, and wise sayings of some of the natives of Teague-Land / ... coullected bee de grete caare and painsh-tauking of oour laurned countree-maun, Mac O Bonnielabbero of Drogheda, Knight of the Mendicant Order.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28551</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3437A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5153</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12270176</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12270176</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58213</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28551)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58213)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 126:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Bogg-witticisms, or, Dear joy's common-places being a compleat collection of the most profound punns, learned bulls, elaborate quibbles, and wise sayings of some of the natives of Teague-Land / ... coullected bee de grete caare and painsh-tauking of oour laurned countree-maun, Mac O Bonnielabbero of Drogheda, Knight of the Mendicant Order.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 59 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Evidansh swear-all in Lack-Plaush Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l.] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1682?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of publication from NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>English wit and humor.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58213:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58213:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Bogg-Witticiſms: OR, <hi>Dear Ioy's</hi> Common-Places. BEING A Compleat Collection of the moſt Profound <hi>Punns,</hi> Learned <hi>Bulls,</hi> Elaborate <hi>Quibbles,</hi> and Wiſe <hi>Sayings</hi> of ſome of the Natives of <hi>Teague-Land.</hi> Shet fourd vor Generaul Nouddificau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion: And Coullected bee de grete Caare and Painſh-Tauking of oour Laurned Countree-maun, <hi>Mac O Bonniclabbero</hi> of <hi>Drogheda,</hi> Knight of the <hi>Mendicant</hi> Order.</p>
            <p>PRINTED For Evidanſh <hi>Swear-all</hi> in <hi>Lack-Plauſh</hi> Lane.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Price Bound Two Shilling Six-Pence</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:58213:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58213:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THe <hi>Bulls</hi> and <hi>Witticiſms,</hi> that have too frequently dropt from the Mouths of <hi>Dear Joys,</hi> have made them ſo Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, that they are become the Diſcourſe and Entertainment of almoſt all ſorts of Companies: And in troth, they are generally ſo full of Diverſion, that they would almoſt force a Smile from <hi>Heraclitus.</hi> Nothing more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commends them, than the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Stupidity or Simplicity of the <hi>Natives;</hi> ſo that they do not
<pb facs="tcp:58213:3"/>appear like little <hi>Contrivances,</hi> but purely the Effects of their <hi>Notions</hi> and <hi>Miſtakes</hi> of <hi>Things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Welchmen</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> had a long time Engroſſed all the <hi>Table-Talk</hi> of the Town; and the <hi>Jests</hi> and <hi>Stories</hi> that were Related concerning them, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed inſtead of a <hi>Song,</hi> or a <hi>Fidle.</hi> But <hi>Teague</hi> and his Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men have clearly Baffled Saint <hi>Taffy</hi> and Saint <hi>Andrew,</hi> for down-right <hi>Dunſtable, Blunder,</hi> and <hi>Punn;</hi> who are no more to be compared to them, than the little Sooty Lanthorns in <hi>Smithfield,</hi> to the Radiant Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying Lights in <hi>Cheapſide.</hi> The following <hi>Collection</hi> preſents you with great variety of the
<pb facs="tcp:58213:3"/>moſt <hi>Novel</hi> and <hi>Facetious;</hi> which may ſerve as Wallnuts with a Glaſs of Wine, and be an excellent Relief againſt an uneaſie and ſullen Melancholy. The <hi>Collector</hi> has not the Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to perſwade himſelf, that they will Sute every Temper; there being ſome ſo perverſe, and implacable, as never to like any Mans humour but their own; and, like the Crow, think their own Off-ſpring faireſt: I fairly leave ſuch to the Election of their own Appetites; and ſhall not preſume to force my Sauce upon their Palats. I have no apprehenſion, that any Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Reader can Interpret any thing herein contained, as a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional
<pb facs="tcp:58213:4"/>or Particular Reflection; that being the moſt Remote imaginable, both from the <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector</hi>'s Inclination and Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And I ſhall, for once, preſume to Obviate any ſuch undue Reflection, with the Motto of the Royal Garter; <hi>Honi Soit Qui Mal Y Penſe.</hi> But if you will have it in ſhort, The deſign of Publiſhing them is this; That whilſt the <hi>Reader</hi> enjoys himſelf and Friend over a Glaſs of Wine, the <hi>Book-ſeller</hi> and I may have a Glaſs of Wine to make Merry over too.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:58213:4"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE By Teague.</head>
            <p>BEE Shaint <hi>Pautrick,</hi> de Dee'l tauke mee noow, but Y caun remaumber de time, vaan mee Fauder vaſh maukeretorne of a grate dele vary muſt moniſh, bee Creeſht; and dat vaſh conſharn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sheepſh, and Coweſh, and Hourſhes, and Piggſh too, bee Shaint <hi>Antonie;</hi> and vaat iſh de maater, in de Dee'lliſh Naume, indeed, dat dere iſh noe mony for mine <hi>Bullſh,</hi> indeed? And, in fait, <hi>Dear Joy,</hi> Dee'l tauke mee, bot dey bee of de largeſht kind too, indeede; and dey bee aull of de
<pb facs="tcp:58213:5"/>right ſhtraine too, noow. Heare iſh no Leeving vidout Monyſh, in fait, <hi>Dear Joy,</hi> and mee Beef and Broat Voman, (de Dee'l tauke de Beeſh) ſhe vill not Trosht mee for Tree haulf-Penſh more, for mine Dinnar indeed. Y hauve mauke try to binde mee ſhelfe Prentiſh to ſhome boudy, to gat Monyſh; and, bee Shaint <hi>Pautricks</hi> Bonnet, dere iſh noe boudy vill haufe mee, noow. And Y did tinke to binde mee ſhelfe Prantiſh to ſhome Evidanſh-mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker; and bee Shaint <hi>Bridgat,</hi> dat bee aull oout of de Fauſhion, and every Boudy muſht bee Houneſht, bee Creeſht, and dere iſh noe Plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes to bee gott noow. And I vaſh juſht a-goeing to coume and manke haung upon mee-ſhelfe indeed, and
<pb facs="tcp:58213:5"/>to put de maater oout of aul dout; vor dere vaſh none Leeving vor <hi>Teague</hi> any longar. And vaſh not diſh a veery ſhad cauſh indeed? Vaan Y vaſh in diſh Condiſhion, and vaſh juſht mank tinking upon haunging, bee Creeſht; dere comeſh a Maun, and lookeſh upon mee Faush in fait; <hi>What is the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter honeſt Lad (ſayes he?)</hi> Bee Creesht, and daat bee veery goodt newsh, to call mee honesht, Y tinke; and Y tall him, de maater vash veery baud indeed, vor y vash in mishurable poore Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shions indeed. Dan hee shay to mee, daat Y musht bee for putting mee shelfe upon good Cheare; daat hee had friendſh voud halpe mee to shome mony, indeed. Bee mee
<pb facs="tcp:58213:6"/>Shalvashion, <hi>Dear Joy,</hi> Y vash for manking veery mush Joy upon mee ſhelf noow; and Y deed shay to hem, indeed; Bee de Mauſh, <hi>Dear Joy,</hi> dee beesht de shivilleſt Parshon in aul de Vorld, in fait; and de Dee'l tauke mee indeed, bot dee hasht mauke mush rejoyshing upon mee noow, too; And Y vood praay dee to doe mee de fauvour, to shew mee de kindnesh, to tall mee vhatdish Friend of dyne ish, daat vill halp mee to shommony indeed; and Y shall bee boond to mauke mee shelfe, and aull de Poshterity of poore <hi>Teague,</hi> over to hem, and hish Haresh, bee Laater of Attur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, in fait noow. <hi>Well then,</hi> (hee deed shay to mee) <hi>If thou canſt furniſh me with ſome good Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb facs="tcp:58213:6"/>Bulls, thou ſhalt have ready mony for them.</hi> Noow, de Dee'l tauke dee, <hi>Dear Joy,</hi> (Y did shay to him) dou hasht mauke mee dede agen, bee mee Shoul; for de Armish did mauke Plundar upon mine Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and did tauke avay aull hish Bullsh, Cowesh, and Horshes too, bee Creesht, before dat Y vash born indeed; Andnoow, if dat be and, Y vill onsh moure tauke haunging into mee Conshideration, indeed; and sho fare dee veell, <hi>Dear Joy. But ſtay,</hi> (he did shay to mee agen) <hi>I do not mean Horn'd-Beaſts,</hi> my Friend; <hi>we Citizens have enow of that ſort of</hi> Cattle; <hi>I ſay, I mean a ſort of Comical Joques, called</hi> Bulls, <hi>That are a Prepoſterouskind of ſpeaking; when you return my
<pb facs="tcp:58213:7"/>meaning as by miſtake: In ſhort, I do not mean the Bull</hi> For <hi>the Mouth; but the bull</hi> Of <hi>the Mouth; and ſuch as theſe, and any other pleaſant Stories for Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, are the Market I would be at.</hi> Enoow! Enoow! <hi>Dear Joy,</hi> (Y did shay) Y doe under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shtand dee, indeed; it ish shome Shtories consharning mee shalfe, and <hi>Bryan,</hi> and halfe a Doshen more of ush: Bee mee Shoul, Y can tall dee abondansh indeed. And if dee vilt bee sho shivil, to mauke paymensh of shom Monysh, Y vill tall dee sho many ash a vhole Drove at dish time, indeed: And ven vee doe meet agen, vee vill hauve de toddar bout, hee mee Broguesh, in fait noow.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58213:7"/>
            <head>Bogg Witticiſmes.</head>
            <p>NEceſſity hath been often the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Ingenuity, and it will appear a very great Truth, if the following Story be Conſidered. For <hi>Dennis</hi> had a long time been waiting, and <hi>mauking Petiſhion for a Plauſh,</hi> until Fob grew ſo low that it could not produce three half<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence a day for the <hi>Ireiſh Ordinary:</hi> So that as he was taking the matter into ſerious conſideration, and End of Gold and Silver Woman paſſed by with her uſual Cry, Any <hi>old Sattin,</hi> or <hi>Taffaty,</hi> or <hi>Velvet,</hi> and <hi>old Lace</hi> take mony for it. <hi>Noo Y prethee dear Joy</hi> (quoth <hi>Dennis</hi> to the Woman) <hi>what iſh the priſhe dat thee vilt geef for good Lace? Y have ſo much at me Lodging as coſt about three poundſh, and Y will goe and feſh it for thee preſhantly, if thee vilt give me ſhom mony for it?</hi> The wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man replyed, that ſhe never gave above 5 <hi>s.</hi> an ounce for the beſt, when it was well burnt, and cleaned: <hi>Dan Y woud be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheech
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58213:8"/>thee to call at me Lodgingſh an hour after thiſh time, and be Creeſht Y will burn me Lanſh for thee now, and thee ſhalt have it indede;</hi> pray where is your Lodging? ſaid the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>why me Lodgingiſh at the bird and Baby he Sharing-Croſs indeed, and Devil tauke me if thee vilt call thee ſhalt have me beſht lauſh, and it iſh very good indede.</hi> The woman went her way, and <hi>Dennis</hi> repairs to his Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, taking his beſt Lace Crevat, and Ruffles, and ſet them on fire, preſerving the aſhes carefully, and making them up in a piece of paper. The woman came at the time, and <hi>Dennis</hi> brought her down the paper of Aſhes: what is this (ſays the woman) that you have brought me? <hi>By me Shoul what doſht dee tinke it iſh? why is iſh all my beſht Lauce, and Y have burnt it very care fully for thee indede, and noo Y woud have the take notiſh what iſh de wayt of it, and give me de mony for it.</hi> Doſt think me mad (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed the woman) to give Mony for a few aſhes; I tell thee, I do not uſe to deal in ſuch ware. <hi>Now the Deevil tauke me</hi> (<hi>ſaid</hi> Dennis) <hi>it iſh me beſht Lauce Crevat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Cuffs, and Y had them of me Captain the other day, and noo Y have burnt them for d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vilt geeve me noting for it. Deevil tauke the for a Biſh, you Son of a Wore, Y will mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sware upon thee before the Juſtice for putting a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58213:8"/>great cheat upon me, baſhe Slut indeed. Where iſh the mony for the burnt Laſhe now, ha?</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thee get home, you bog-trotting Owle (quoth the woman) burn thy Mantle and Brogues, it may be that may yield thee ſhom mony to buy a Plauſh; you ſimple Scoundrel thou. <hi>Be Creeſht</hi> (<hi>quoth</hi> Dennis) <hi>thee beeſt come to put abuſe upon me, Deevil tauke me for a Son of a Whore, but Y will make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge upon thee for me beſht Lauſhe now, yeſh indede.</hi> The Scuffle continued a long time before <hi>Dennis</hi> could be convinced of his Error; until at length all that heard it laughed heartily at his Ignorance, which made him go out of the Houſe in great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>2.</head>
               <p>A Bird in hand is worth two in a Buſh they ſay, and <hi>Own</hi> made ſome proof of it; For his Lady gave him a <hi>Canary</hi> Bird to preſent from her to a Lady of her ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, now <hi>Owen</hi> had ſeen the boys houſe their Sparrows under their Hatts, and (being taken with the humour) puts the <hi>Canary</hi> Bird up under his; but in the way as he ways going with his preſent, a Coach paſſed by, behind which was a Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Owens,</hi> who put off his Hatt to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58213:9"/>
                  <hi>Owen,</hi> and our dear Joy anſwered his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement with much reſpect, not minding the <hi>Canary</hi> Bird in the Garret; at length he came to the Ladies houſe, and asked the Porter if his Lady were within, who anſwered him, Yes. <hi>Why then</hi> (<hi>quoth</hi> Owen) <hi>Y prethee tell her that Y am belonging to ſuch a Lady, and be me Shoul Y have brought her a preſhent from my Lady:</hi> Whereupon, <hi>Owen</hi> being called in, delivers himſelf after this manner, <hi>Me Laudy preſents her Sharviſh to thee, and has ſhent thee</hi> (at that he began to feel on his crown, to look in his hart, and to bruſh the locks of his wigg, looking eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way about him:) What hath ſhe ſent? (quoth the Lady,) <hi>Be Creeſht it waſh a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Shinning Bird, and the Deevil tauke me Joy it iſh come to nothing at all now.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>3.</head>
               <p>Dear Joy paying great Devotion before a certain old Image at a Church in <hi>France;</hi> It hapened that the rotten Figure fell upon him, and bruiſed him very much, ſo that he was forced to keep within doors for a conſiderable time, and then coming again to the ſame Church, he ſaw a very fine new Image ſet up in the ſame place: to which he addreſſed himſelf after this ſort;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58213:9"/>
                  <hi>Be me Shoul dear Joy, Deevil tauke me if the doſht not look as pleaſhant as mine own Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heart, and Y can ſcarce forbear to mauke Prayer to thee, but thy Father leaped down upon me and waſh like to breake my Neck; and by Creeſht Y have no mind to truſt thee for all thy ſine looks.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>4.</head>
               <p>When <hi>Tangier</hi> was in the poſſeſſion of his Majeſty of <hi>Great Brittain,</hi> a certain <hi>Iriſh</hi> man was Servant to a Major there; the Major happened to die in his Servants debt for Wages, and about three years after his Maſters death, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered a Petition to the Governour to this effect.</p>
               <p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
                     <body>
                        <head>The Petition.</head>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>May it Pleaſhe thy Grauſhes Neckſhellence,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>THere iſh happen to be great Falling-out between me Maſhter Major <hi>White,</hi> and me Shelfe, conſharning ſhom monyſh that iſh owing unto me from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhelfe,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58213:10"/>and be Creeſht, dear Joy, Y vill tall thee it iſh for Wages; nov the Devil tauke me but Y will make Petition upon thee, that thee wouldſt be pleaſed to do me the favour to do me the kindneſh, to tauke order wid him that he may pay me the mony; and be me Shalwaſhion Y will tell thee, Y will buy Comiſhion of thee for a Captain or a Collonelſh plauſh Indede. So Y adviſh thee to tauke ſhpeaſhial caure that I may hauve what iſh due to me, for the Deevil tauke thee if Y can tell what to do for want of it In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dede. And if thee own dear ſhelfe cannot tauke order for me, Y will pray thee to make petiſhion fexe me upon his Majeſhties Grauce
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58213:10"/>into <hi>England,</hi> that Y may not have Cheat put upon me, for what iſh my own Indede.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Sho Y reſht, Dear Joy, thy Grauſhes hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sharvant <hi>M.D.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>The Governour having conſidered the Contents of the Petition, began to Enquire what this Major <hi>White</hi> was, and being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed that the Gentleman had been dead for three years, he could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear ſmiling at the downright Ignorance of the Petitioner, and order'd him to be called in, when he ſpake to him to this purpoſe: Friend, I have read thy Paper here, and I find thee wouldſt have me order one Major <hi>White</hi> to pay thee mony; where is this Major <hi>White?</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Why, if thee wilt come along wid me Y
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58213:11"/>will ſhow thee whare he iſh put under a Shtone indede.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gov.</speaker>
                  <p>What! is he dead then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yeſh be Creeſht iſh he.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gov.</speaker>
                  <p>How long?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It iſh! let me ſhee, it iſh about tree Yearſh, dear Joy.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gov.</speaker>
                  <p>This is very pretty, and thou wou'dſt have me ſue him in the Grave for thee, I warrant thee? ha!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yeſh, yeſh, Devil tauke me Y wou'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dede.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gov.</speaker>
                  <p>It is not like that ſuch a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men died in debt to his Servants, but the Dead pay no Debts.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Be me Shoul dat iſh very pretty, dear Joy! than it iſh nothing but to dye and put the Cheat upon every body for what iſh due to them! be the Maſh thiſh iſh de greateſt Cheat in the wholl world now! Y will die too be Creeſht, and put the great Cheat upon every body too indede.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <p>The Governour was ready to burſt with the Comedy, and ordered his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to make the <hi>Iriſh-man</hi> drink, and ſo diſmiſt him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>5.</head>
               <p>A certain Collonel having loſt one of his Hands in his Majeſties Service, and an
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58213:11"/>Artificial Hand of Steel put on, and it was done with that Curioſity, that he could hold his Fork in it or take up a cup of Beer, or command his Horſe with it, but ſtill it appeared to be Steel, and was very finely polliſhed. It happened a Dear Joy was waiting upon his Maſter at Table, who dined with the Collonel; he took great notice of the Steel Hand, at length (quoth he to the Collonels Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant) <hi>Y prethee tell me, waſh dy Maſhter born wid dat Hand? be Creeſht it iſh very ſtrange an Iron Hand ſhou'd grow ſo big, iſh it not?</hi> the Servant told the Iriſh-mans queſtion to the Table, who laught heartily at it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>6.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Naturam Expellas</hi> Fune <hi>licet uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Recurret.</hi> Once a Taylor and always a Thief, was an Addage founded upon good Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; or if that will not Convince you of the unalterableneſs of mens natural Diſpoſitions, perhaps the enſuing Story may.</p>
               <p>It is ſaid a certain Mac-lander had liſted himſelf in the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Army in <hi>Flanders,</hi> but (not well approving of that Service) had deſerted his Colours, and was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon apprehended, and tied up to Deſtiny
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58213:12"/>upon a Gibbet not far from <hi>Bruges;</hi> A Country-man paſſing by with his Cart in little time after the body had been truſſed up, and conſidering him to be a proper Fellow; (having likewiſe felt, and found his body very warm, and that his breath had not quite deſerted it) began to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſome thoughts of taking him down, and endeavouring to reſtore him again to the number of the Living; accordingly, when he had driven the Cart under the Tree, and received the body in it, he cut the Hemp, and drave him home, where there was immediate care taken, by bleeding, fomenting, and other requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite means for his recovery, ſo that in few hours he was as if he had never been ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended: He had a remembrance that he had been drag'd to the place of Execution, but not the leaſt apprehenſion of what had been done to him afterwards. The honeſt Country-man told him the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he had found him in, and the Cure, and means that had been taken for his recovery, <hi>Mac.</hi> ſeemed very penitent, and reſolved upon a new Courſe of Life; Complaining much <hi>upon de Shaints</hi> upon <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> ſays he) <hi>be Creeſht Y have mauke abundanſh of Shuplicauſion, aund Y have been ſhivil to dem indede, Aund eet upon aall daat
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58213:12"/>neever one of dem waſh ſho kind to come ſhaare me, or to taake de Shtring from me Neck in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed: Noow de plaague devil dem, for Y am ſhatiſhfied de beeſht honeſhter man dan dey be, Y have mauke much ſharviſh, and kindneſh up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on dem, aund dey waſh not come to ſhave me, aund Y vill not come to dem again indede; but Y vill be vid dee, aund vill mauke all me Shar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh upon dee, in fait, and let dem aall be ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved aſh dey vou'd let me be ſharved, indede.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Country man hoped that he had gained a ſtout Servant, and was very well ſatisfied in what he had done. But there are a ſort of Horſes, bred in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Country, that all the art and care of the moſt Exquiſite Jocky can never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim or break from their <hi>Jades tricks,</hi> they will ſtill retain their unlucky Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and it is not improbable that many of the Natives of that Land are of the ſame diſpoſition with their <hi>beaſts</hi> (that is to ſay) they are not Reclaimable. For this very <hi>Mac.</hi> we are now ſpeaking of, no ſooner was intruſted by the honeſt <hi>Flanderkin,</hi> to aſſiſt him in the buſineſs of his Husbandry; no ſooner was he <hi>Warm,</hi> but <hi>(like the Snake)</hi> his <hi>Poyſon returned</hi> to him: his <hi>Mac. qualities regained</hi> upon him, he made a ſhift to rob the honeſt Country man of what he could pillage, and rid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58213:13"/>with one of his beſt Horſes to the bargain, and this within three days after the good man had ſaved his Life: the <hi>Flanderkin</hi> and his Son ſoon perceiving ſomething amiſs, purſued the ungrateful wretch, and in a League or two of the Village found him wallowing in Brandy, <hi>(a Baſtard ſort of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſquebah)</hi> He was imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately bound, and Manackled, carried to his Maſters houſe, and there <hi>once more</hi> put into the <hi>Cart,</hi> and conveyed to the place from whence he had been <hi>repriev'd</hi> from <hi>Execution,</hi> when he came underneath the <hi>Fertile Tree,</hi> and had the ſecond time taken the form of hanging into his conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, there was a great <hi>hoo boob</hi> raiſed within him, by reaſon of ſomething of regret he had to make his <hi>Exit</hi> on that faſhion: But for greater <hi>decorum</hi> of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion <hi>(for want of a Ghoſtly Father)</hi> he made his Confeſſion to his Executioners in manner and form following <hi>(that iſh to ſhay) Yt iſh a plaugy Cauſh indede (me Dear Joy) dat dee vilt tye me up to diſh dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villiſh <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwholſome plauſh agen be Chreeſht; Noow de deevil tauke me, aund be Shaint</hi> Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trickſh <hi>Shoo-bookle! it iſh very haard indede! Me Fadder waſh a Cut-Troat be de Maſh, in fait; and he had great Liberty of Conſhianſh, to do every Ting: aund be Creeſht! hoo! hoo!
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58213:13"/>hoo! woo! woo! it iſh bloudy haard indede! Noow to maake two Murdar upon me body indede, Furſht de King of Shpainſh Laaweſh, for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſharting me Colourſh, indede! and now (deare Joy) be Chreeſht dee vilt hang me too, for ſhom Piſhtolſh, and a plaugy drooukan Guelding of a Maure, (be Chreeſht) dat ſhtop at the next Braandy Shop, aund noow de deevil tauke de Maure too indede, daat ſhe cou'd not run avay furdar vid me, aund be de Maſh I muſht be haung'd twiſh noow for de Jaud'ſh treekſh of diſh plaugy Maure indede! hoo! hoo! woo! boo! boo! Noow de deevil tauke dee too noow, aund vaat muſht Y be haung'd twiſbe for noow? heare iſh dy Maure agen indede, aund heare iſh de Piſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolſh, aal but Shix upon me fait noow! Aund Y predee, deare Joy, lat uſh be friendsh agaain, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dede! aund Y vill Sware me shelfe to de Devil for dee indede:</hi> Hark ye, hark ye, (dear Joy) quoth the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> I do you no wrong, I found you hear in a <hi>Stinking pickle,</hi> I carried you home, and dry'd ye, and made ye Clean; in fine, I ſav'd ye once from the Gallows, and ye have ſerv'd me according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and now let the next Man that has a mind to be Cheated, take thee down agen, for I will e'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>leave thee</hi> as I found <hi>thee,</hi> and ſo <hi>Farewell and be hang'd,</hi> that's twice God bu'y.</p>
               <p>Having ſo ſaid, they left there the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling Objet to ſcare the Paſſengers, who were in great ſurpriſe to ſee the ſame Man
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58213:14"/>that was hang'd for three days before, and they thought buried the ſame Night, come again and hang upon the ſame Gibbet, and that now he had got <hi>Boots</hi> on, whereas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he had none, (for you muſt know the Farmer, and his Son were in ſuch haſt to be rid of him, that they e'n tied him up in the ſame garbe that they found him,) this (as I was ſaying) mightily ſurpriſed them, and they thought the Devil had ſent him <hi>Poſt</hi> back again.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>7.</head>
               <p>A Gentleman's Footman in the Country took an occaſion to Gallant the Kitching Maid (between whom, and himſelf, there had paſſed many an amorous Intrigue) and leading her into the Orchard in a Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Evening they happened to ſit down under a Pipping Three, to entertain them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with a little private Converſe; It was about the buſineſs of <hi>Comfortable Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance;</hi> 
                  <q rend="inline">Be Shaint <hi>Pautricks</hi> Shoo-horne (quoth <hi>Donell</hi>) Y have very much great deal of Love for dee, Y vill put ſhom kiſh upon dee fauſh, aund maake ſhom Child upon dee body indede!</q> and ſo <hi>Donnel</hi> put what he had ſaid in execution: Now it happened that upon that very Tree was a Spark, who had come thither to borrow ſome of the Fruit, and upon their approach
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58213:14"/>to that place, kept himſelf very cloſe, but ſo that he ſaw and heard all that paſſed. When the Exerciſe was over (ſaid the Miſs to the Lover) O! <hi>Donnel,</hi> you and I have often had theſe enjoyments; but if I ſhould prove with Child, what care would there be taken of me, or the Infant? <q rend="inline">Noow de Deevil tauke me (replyed he) be de Maſh it iſh unſhivil for dee to put ſhuch queſtion upon me indede; pradee lat me ſhom more kiſh upon de fauſh in fait, and dere iſh one above vill tauke caure for de Child and dee too be Creeſht.</q> That's a damn'd lye (quoth the Fellow in the Tree) for I never intend to take care for any Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards, but of my own getting. Upon which words they both ran away in great confuſion; <hi>Donnel</hi> crying out, <q rend="inline">Be me ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waſhion de deevil haſh been vitneſs to vat vee haave don indede; aund if dee beeſht mauke vid Child, he himſhelfe ſhall be de Godfader in fait.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>8.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bryan</hi> having hurted one of his Legs, that it was much ſwollen, and his Maſter ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving occaſion to ſend him a conſiderable Journey into the Country; <hi>Bryan</hi> went to the Shoomaker, directing him to make one of his Boots pretty much bigger than the other. When the Boots were brought
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58213:15"/>home, and to be put on, <hi>Bryan</hi> fell into a great fumigation with the Shoomaker, Swaring at him, <q rend="inline">Be de ſhoul of mine Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der aund me Graundfader, let a touſhand deevilſh pull me to peeſhes, if dou beeſht not de greateſht Fool dat ever waſh borne upon a woman; vaat de deevil canſh dee not undarſhtand vaat iſh ſho plain ſhaid to dee, Y did bad dee mauke one of me Botoſh bggar dan de toddar, aund be Chreeſht de ſhimpleton have mauke one Leſhar dan de toddar: preddee dear Joy! dee maiſht tauke dem home vid dy none ſhelfe again indede, day vill not be upon ſharviſh for me be Creeſht noow. La.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>9.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mao Clan,</hi> and his Man being travelling together upon the Road, and one of his Horſes was lamed by a prick of a Nail, the other had received a ſtrain in one Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: <q rend="inline"> Be Shaint <hi>Pantricks</hi> Tobacco-ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and Shaint <hi>Brigatsh</hi> Thimble, noow de deevil reed avaay upon me in fait, but one of deshe Horshes ish boat doown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reeght laam, in fait! yeet be me Mash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>booke, de blaake Maure be a shtoutar Horſe dan de vite Naag indede, Deevil take me if Y have not maake ride upon me laame Beetch indede, dat mine Arsh ish sho shore ash de baak of mine haund,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58213:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>in fait; plaague deevil de daumn Beech for me, she vill never leave mauke shtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aund faul, before she trow me from de Shadle down Shtairesh, and brauk me Neck, be Creesht. But <hi>Denniſh</hi> (quoth he to his Man) Y vill mauke shpeak upon dee a leetle indede, upon a wheesh foot ish me Maure laume indede? Noow de plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue taake dee in fait, dosht not dee knaw? be Creesht it ish de hander footsh before, creplayed <hi>Denniſh</hi> to his Maſter.) Aund be me Shawl vaat ish de maatre daat dy Naag be sho upreeht laume, Y preddee? Noow de deevil taake dee indede, dear Joy! (replyed <hi>Dennis</hi> to his Maſter again) dosht dee not shee vid dyne Eyshe indede? whee dan Y vill tall de noow, it ish the Rumpe-boan of de reeght Sholdar upon the needar ſide dat is put oout of hish plaush, Joy, aund be Shaint <hi>Antonce,</hi> de deevil tauke me but Y am sho laume daat Y cannot sheet upon de baak of de deevil any longar in fait, noow!</q> They jogg'd on upon their cripled Jades for a long time, ſometimes curſing themſelves, ſometimes their Horſes, ſometimes their Saints, or any thing they thought on; till at length they ſtumbled upon a Farriers Shop, in a ſmall Country Village upon the Road; they got up to him, <hi>Ashke hish audvishe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout theire Roſinante's;</hi> Vulcan told them, one muſt have his foot drawn, and the other
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58213:16"/>be rowled on the Shoulder, and that they muſt have many days reſt, before he could warrant a Cure upon them. <q rend="inline">Deevil rasht dare Sholesh in dare grauvesh indede, (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed <hi>Mac Clan</hi>) voo de pocksh vou'd be sho plaug'd vid a couple of deevillish bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, in fait' Y veesh vid aul me Shoul, indede! dat Y haud mauke von lushtie auble Horſe for boat de beechesh, in fait, La!</q>
               </p>
               <p>Say you ſo (quoth the Farrier, who perceived the <hi>Simplicity</hi> of the <hi>Animalls,</hi>) If you will leave the Horſes to my care; I doubt not but for both of them I may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure a ſtout Nagg, againſt your return this way: <hi>Vid aul mine harte deare Joy,</hi> (ſaid Mac Clan) <hi>Y will mauke put dem upon dye Caure be me ſhoul, and Y will mauke caull upon dee about tree Weekſh after yeſhterday, aund Y will geeve dee ſhatiſhfaction for dy kindn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſh to me Horſhes, indede! aund be Creeſht deare Joy, ſhe dou mauke a propper Galding oout of dem too, indede!</hi> Let me alone for that (replyed the Smith) and ſo they parted, leaving their Cattle to his care, whilſt they purſued the reſt of their Journy on <hi>foot-back,</hi> about fifty Miles: during their abſence (you muſt know) the Farrier had cured, and put off the two Beaſts belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to <hi>Mac Clan,</hi> and his Man <hi>Dennis,</hi> and had <hi>got Mony by the bargin:</hi> And had provided an old rotten <hi>Keffill</hi> to accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58213:16"/>the Sparke at his return: By the way you are to underſtand, that <hi>Mac's</hi> Mare was black, and <hi>Dennis's</hi> Nagg was white, and the Beaſt that <hi>Vulcan</hi> had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided was <hi>Pyed,</hi> anſwerable to both their Colours: So that when our Sparke re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, and ſaw the <hi>Animal</hi> that was provided for him, he concluded with himſelf that it had (in earneſt) been <hi>Compounded</hi> of his <hi>Black</hi> Mare, and <hi>Denis</hi>'s <hi>White</hi> Nagg. <hi>Noow be ſhaint Bartelemew's Butcharing Knife</hi> (deare Joy,) (Says <hi>Mac Clan</hi> to the Farrier) <hi>let mee ſhinke up to de Eareſh in de neckſht boog be Creeſht, but dee art ſhartainly de mann of de moſht Confounded Shienſh in de Vorld, in fait, for dere iſh de ſhame Collourſh be Creeſht, de very ſhame Coomplack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion aſh me maure vaſh, and de ſame vite bairſh aſh vas upon Denniſh's Horſhe; be de Maſs, it iſh like boat one of de too; But Y vill mauke a leetle ſhpeaking upon dee (deare Joy) What iſh de reaſhon daat diſh horſhe iſh ſhoe leetle, aund be me ſhould indede, dee haſht put too Horſhes into hiſh body? Y ſhould mauke Expectaſhionſh dat de too Horſhes ſhould mauke one tall, Shtrong, and luſhty Gualding, indede?</hi> You muſt conſider this is but a Colt yet, being not three weeks ſince it was made, but when it is full growne, it will be a mighty Beaſh indeed. D-<hi>ſht dee beare daat Denniſh</hi> (quoth Mac to his Man) <hi>be Creeſht it iſh a Colt</hi> (he ſhay) <hi>aund it vill be a veery grate Horſhe, van he be
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58213:17"/>grown op to Manſh Eſhtate. Be Chreeſht diſh be the verey Larned Man in fait; Deevil tauke me deare Joy, Y will mauke publicaaſhion of dy great ſhkill in every plauſh indede.</hi> In fine, they came to agreement what the Farrier was to have for making up the two lame Horſes, into one; <hi>Mac</hi> pay'd him his demands, put one of the Sadles upon <hi>Pye,</hi> and <hi>Mac</hi> gat upon the outſide of him, the other Sadle was girt on upon <hi>Dennis,</hi> who followed his Maſter on foot. They parted from the Farrier, not without great ſuſpicion of his being a Conjurer; <hi>Dennis</hi> was once under ſome fear, when the Saddle was faſtned to his back, Leaſt the Man of Art ſhould have converted him to a Horſe too. They had not travail'd farr before <hi>Dennis</hi> percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his Maſters Horſe to be lame of all four, and upon that Ocaſion addreſs'd himſelf to him after this ſort. <q rend="inline">Noow de Deevill tauke dee, deare Joy; de two Horſhes daat was maake up into diſh Cattle, vaſh laume but upon too ſhideſh, indede; but in fait diſh Gualding iſh lame upon all de forwre footſh, La: ſhee ſhee vat a damn fool dou art <hi>(replayed Mac)</hi> aund be Creeſht did not de Larned man Shay it waſh a Colt; and deevill tauke me, hiſh footſh vill be tandar diſh great vile, till hiſh naileſht be grow hard and ſtrong indede.</q> Many more Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were made upon their Miraculous
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58213:17"/>Beaſt; and ſome ſay <hi>Mac</hi> was upon <hi>mauk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Petiſhion to mauke ſhow of his Twin-Barb at the Bell Shavage.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>10</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pautrick</hi> had been in the Warrs in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> and after his return, ſitting in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with ſome of his brother Brogues, he was vanting what dangers he had gon through, what exploits he had don, and amongſt the reſt that he had cut off one of the Enemies Legs, <q rend="inline">Be Creeſht <hi>Pautrick (ſays one of them)</hi> dee ſhoudſht have diſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, dee Paike at him, annd hauve Cutt hiſh heed off from hiſh body. Noow de Deevill tauke me <hi>(replyed be)</hi> daat iſh veery true indede, but be de Mauſh deare Joy, Y caume too laute for daat indede, for be me ſhalwaſhion hiſh heed vaſh tauken avay before indede now.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>11.</head>
               <p>One of deare-Joy-Land had a Son that ſerved a Gentleman here, in quality of his Foot-man; after he had been in <hi>England</hi> for ſome time, his Friends (upon ſome Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion) writ over for a Teſtimonial whether he was alive, or not, upon Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting his Acquaintance about the matter, they adviſed him to get a Scrivener to draw
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58213:18"/>it, and get it ſigned by the hands of the moſt Credible Countrey men that were known to his Relations: This being all done accordingly, he was told he might ſend it by Poſt to <hi>Cheſter,</hi> and after the Pacquet Boat would take Care of it: One night his Maſter ſent him to the Poſt houſe with Letters; and he had ſome Inclination to have put in his Certificate, but fearing the Pacquet Boat might miſcarry, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to carry it himſelf; His Maſter ſaw him no more in ſix weeks, at length he appears again, and being asked what had occaſion'd him to abſent himſelf ſo long; he made anſwer to this purpoſe. <q rend="inline">Be Creeſht me Relauſhionſh deed mauke ſhand a Leetre, daat Y muſht ſhend dem a Shartificate daat Y waſh alive; Y haad geet a skriviſhner to mauke vrite upon de Pauper for me, aund it vaſh ſhined be me Friendſh here indede, but upon feare daat de Pacquat Boat ſhould miſcary, be Creeſht Y did mauke goe, and carry eet me ſhelfe indede, daat van day ſhee de Shar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificatſh, dey maight tinke it vaſh meen awn ſhelfe daat vaſh alive indede.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>12</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Teague</hi> having been Obliged to wait upon his Maſter to <hi>Edingbourgh,</hi> where he conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued for ſome time, at his returne to <hi>London</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:58213:18"/>fell in Company of ſome of his old Aquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, how doeſt thou like that Country Teague (ſayes one of them) <q rend="inline">Y will tall dee be Creeſht <hi>(replyed he)</hi> Y vaſh Sheeke all de time Y vaſh dare indede; And be ſhaint <hi>Pautrick</hi> if Y haud Leeved daure 'till diſh time, be de Mauſh, de Deevill tauke me indede, but Y ſhou'ed hauve been deed noow for Sheaven Yearſh agoe, deare Joy, upon me fait it iſh true indede.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>13</head>
               <p>A certain Lord having a Nimble <hi>Bog-Trotter</hi> to his ſervant which uſe to travell with him when he rode and wou'd make as quick ſpeed as his Horſe let him ride never ſo hard, This Nobleman having occaſion to ſend his ſervant to a Gentleman of his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance who lived about a dozen Miles from him, he call'd his Man to him over Night, and ſaid <hi>Teague</hi> (for ſo the fellow was named) I muſt ſend you to morrow very early in the morning to Mr.... pray remember, to which <hi>Teague</hi> reply'd <hi>au my ſhaul Joy I ſaul remember very well,</hi> In the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Teague</hi> roſe very Early and away he trots to this Gentlemans houſe leaving his Maſter (as ſuppoſed) a ſleep, and being come <hi>Teague</hi> knosked at the Door, and was let in, Who preſently ask'd for the Gentleman, he Maſter of the Houſe, to which the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58213:19"/>anſwered he was not ſtirring; <hi>Teague</hi> ſaid <q rend="inline">be Chreesht I muſt ſpeake with him I did come from the Lord... my Maſter.</q> The Servant went &amp; acquainted his Maſter thereof, (thinking it had been ſome Urgent affair that <hi>Teague</hi> ſhould come 12. miles ſo ſoon in the morning.) Whereupon his Mr. having a great reſpect for the Lord (and believing it buſineſs of Moment) ordered <hi>Teague</hi> to come up to his Chamber, And the Gentleman ſaid how now <hi>Teague,</hi> what news doe you bring from My Lord your Mr. that you are here to Early, to which <hi>Teague</hi> anſwered, <hi>be Chreſt I cano tell,</hi> how does my Lord quoth the Gent. <hi>Indeed very well, ſaid Teague,</hi> what is your Errant or buſineſs with me <hi>Teague,</hi> (quoth the Gent.) Quoth Teague <q rend="inline"> be Chreſt &amp; St. Patrick I cannot tell, My Lord did call me to him over night and ſaid I muſt come to thee this morning, yes indeed, &amp; he did charge me to remember it, and be Chreſt thou canſt witneſs I have not forgat it for thou ſeeſt I am here with thee,</q> 
                  <hi>quoth the Gent.</hi> 
                  <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>is this all,</hi>
                  </q> quoth <hi>Teague</hi> 
                  <q rend="inline">au my ſhaul I doe not know any more, and ſo I will goe home (Dear Joy) to my Maſter and tell him I did remember to come to thee</q> (quoth the Gentleman) now I think on't <hi>Teague,</hi> you muſt ſtay a little while, I have ſomething to ſend to your Maſter, which you come for, <hi>be Chreeſh</hi> (<hi>quoth</hi> Teague) <hi>I cano tell:</hi> Then the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58213:19"/>began to think how he should be reveng'd of this Rogue that had thus di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb'd him to no purpoſe, at length he Conſidered he had an ugly ſtone Morter which he did not value, which Mortar he gave <hi>Teague</hi> and told him, he came for that Mortar, and that his Maſter had ſent him purpoſely for it; The Mortar weighed about 80 l. which <hi>Teague</hi> gott upon his Back, and took his leave of the Gentleman, many a face and many a Curſe he did make at the Mortar, for it did hurt his back and ſhould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and almoſt grippled poor <hi>Teague,</hi> but he was bound to endure it with Patience, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving brought it home, he had ſome help to get it off his back; And the reſt of his Servants asked him where he had been, for his Lord miſs'd him; To which he was Dumb and would not anſwer any thing for a long while, at laſt My Lord being at a Bouling Green near, ſent to ſee for <hi>Teague,</hi> and to command him to come to him, who came to the Green to My Lord, ſaid the Lord to <hi>Teague</hi> ye plaguy Rogue where have you been all this day, <hi>Teague</hi> made ugly faces and points to his back an ſhoulders (being ſore and gauld by the ſtone ortar) andas often as My Lord ask'd him where he had been, My Lord received no other anſwer but wretched wry faces and pointing to his Shoulders &amp; back, till at length my Lord grew a little angry, Sirra, ſaid he, tell me where
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58213:20"/>you have been &amp; the meaning of your Poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings and wry Mouth, or elſe I will Cudgell your bones, Then <hi>Teague</hi> anſwered, didſt thou not ſay I muſt goe to Mr.... this morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>and be Chreſt I have been with him,</hi> you dam'd Rogue, ſaid My Lord, I told you over night you ſhould goe to him in the morning, but you ſhould have come to me and taken my Errant along with you, <hi>A plague take thee, and they Errant to, I did bring they Errant upon my back be Chreeſt, till I did bruiſe my ſhoulders, and au my ſhoul I ſhal goe no more of thy Errants,</hi> nay <hi>Teague</hi> (quoth my Lord, doe not ſay ſo) what is it you brought from the Gentleman, <hi>be Chreſt thou may'ſt ſee it if thou wilt goe home,</hi> no Teague, ſaid the Lord (being willing that ſome Gentlemen ſhoud ſhare in the mirth that this fellow was like to make among them) goe you home and fetch this Errant that has ſo mortifyed your ſhoulder and let me ſee it, <hi>Teague</hi> goes home and takes up the Morter and brings it to his Maſter upon the Green, and throwes it down there, at which they all laughed heartily that this fellow ſhould be ſo ſordid as to goe to the Gentleman without his Errant, and commended the Gentlemans In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity to puniſh the fool with ſuch a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then. To be ſhort, his Maſter and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany having had ſport enough with his ſowr faces, his pointings and his Errant, his Maſter bid him carry the Mortar home
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58213:20"/>but withall to goe to the Gentleman again, and fetch the Peſtell to the Morter, he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving forgot it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>14.</head>
               <p>Among the Serwants of a Certain Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man were a <hi>Teaguelander,</hi> and a <hi>French man,</hi> and theſe two did ſometimes jarr, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times were mighty loving. It hapned at a certain time that theſe two Sparks were in a hott diſpute about their Country, and their Saints; And de <hi>French man</hi> did ſputter much in Praiſe of his Country, and of St. <hi>Dennis</hi> who was Saint for <hi>France,</hi> ſaying that no Saint in all the World could com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare to St. <hi>Dennis, po po po po po po, Jay war, what St.</hi> Dennis, ſays <hi>Teague,</hi> quoth the <hi>French</hi> man, St. <hi>Dennis</hi> was Saint for <hi>France,</hi> and St. <hi>Dennis</hi> was murdered at <hi>Paris,</hi> and his Head was cutt off, and begar me tell you no lye, when his Head have been Cutt off, St. <hi>Dennis</hi> did ketch up his Head in his hands and he did carry it two leagues after it was cut off in his hands, and there he did faint and fall down, ſo he was buryed in that Place, and there is a Chappell built and called by the Name of St. <hi>Dennis</hi> to this day, and all the Kings of <hi>France</hi> will be Crown'd there the <hi>Teaguelander</hi> did burſt into laughter, and did ſay, <hi>be Chreeſt my Joy thou doeſt make a great Prate of thy St.</hi> Dennis, <hi>but upon my
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58213:21"/>Shalvation St.</hi> Patrick <hi>was far beyond him, St.</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick, <hi>auoth,</hi> the <hi>French man,</hi> What was St Patrick, <hi>Po po po, be Chriſt,</hi> ſays the Iriſh man, <hi>doeſt thou not know St. Patrick,</hi> no begar ſaid the <hi>French man,</hi> me did never hear of an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Saint, <hi>no quoth</hi> Teague, <hi>be Chreſt I ſhau break thy Pate for thee, what doſt thou ſay there be no</hi> Teagueland <hi>Saint,</hi> theſe words cauſed ſome blows, but they were quickly parted, and the <hi>French man</hi> was judged to be in the wrong, becauſe he gave affront to the <hi>Teague lander</hi> in Contradicting him, ſo he did ask the Bog Trotter pardon, and deſired him to goe on upon his ſtory; Then ſaid the Bog Trot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>St. Patrick was Saint for</hi> Ireland, <hi>and be was murdered at</hi> Dublin <hi>in</hi> Ireland, <hi>and his Flead was Curt off, But the Holy Saint did take his Head up and did make to the Sea ſide, reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not to ſtay in that Country where they had ſo ſerv'd him, and coming to the ſea ſide, he did fling himſelf into the Sea, and be did ſwin indeed three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore Leagues, and then he did come on ſhoat, and was o faint that be dyed, and be was buryed, and the Place is called</hi> Holy Head <hi>to this day.</hi> Quoth the <hi>French man,</hi> how did he ſwim, upon his back, quoth the <hi>Iriſh man,</hi> no be Chreſt he did ſwim upon his Belly, and did ſtrike out his hands as I doe now (he ſtriking out his hands in imitation) where ſays the <hi>French man,</hi> did he carry his head then, <hi>Po po po po, Joy, why be Chreſt he did carry it in his Mouth betwixt his Teeth, and indeed and upon my Shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation it is true.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:58213:21"/>
               <head>15</head>
               <p>A certain <hi>Teague</hi> call'd <hi>Comines,</hi> begging of ſome Gentleman ſome Charity, one of the Gentleman ſaid to him, <hi>Comines</hi> why doſt not thou get ſome preferment amongſt thy Country-men, you ſee the King is very kind to your Country-men and gives them Places, and makes ſome Officers in he Army, why dont you put forward, and beg a Lieutenants Place of his Majeſty, or if it be but a Serjeants, it would be better than this Scandalous way of begging; To which <hi>Comines</hi> reply'd, <hi>That the King had made him a Juſtice of Peace in</hi> Teagueland; <hi>and he would not accept of any Preferment in the Army, but that ſome great Men did detain his Papers from him, and ſaid hee, an my ſhoul I canno goe for</hi> Teagueland <hi>till they will give me my Papers.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>16</head>
               <p>The ſaid <hi>Comines</hi> did frequent a certain <hi>Printers Houſe</hi> neer <hi>Charing Croſs,</hi> that the People were weary'd of him, and the Maſter ſaid before a Gentlemans Servant that lodged in his Houſe, I would fain be rid of this Fellow, this <hi>Comines,</hi> for I can never be quiet for him, ſaid the Gentlemans Servant, I will ſhoot him for you if you
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58213:22"/>will, no ſaid the Maſter, I would not have him hurt, no ſaid the Servant I will not hurt him, then ſaid the Maſter doe what you will to him; So <hi>Comines</hi> one day ſtanding with his back to the Window of the back ſhop of the Printer, and the Printer being walking and talking with a Friend, the Gentlemans Servant hapned to came down to the ſhop, and ſpying <hi>Comines</hi> at the Window, Pops out a pocket Piſtoll, and theer being a Pain broke, he fires the Piſtoll under <hi>Comines</hi> ear; It did no further hurt then caus'd his Peruke to ſtink for the preſent, but <hi>Comines</hi> falls down and Cryes Out, <hi>a Poor</hi> Comines <hi>be Chreſt, Poor</hi> Comines <hi>the Kings Evidence is killed, I am Dead, I am Deaf;</hi> The Printer finding ſome red Ink did ſprinckle ſome upon his Face and Cloths as he lay tumbling, ſometimes with his face upward, and his Eyes ſhut, ſometimes on his back, roaring out that he was murdered, and the Kings beſt Evidence ſlain, at length having continued in this maner ſome time, and no Body condoling him (for it was a back Place where few People came) he began to take ſome Courage, and rubbing himſelf with his hands about his Face, he opened his Eyes, and ſaw his hands (as he thought) all bloody, which was only the red Ink, then he Cry'd out louder and Tumbled up and down ſaying <hi>be Chreſt my heart bloud is out, and upon my Shalvation
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58213:22"/>have waſh'd my hands in my heart blood! O for the Soul of St.</hi> Patrick <hi>help poor</hi> Comines <hi>whoſe heart blood is ſpilt for the Kings ſake,</hi> but thoſe which were thereby, did ſo flout and jeer him, that at laſt he did get up upon his Leggs, and did dog trot it away having never ſince been ſeen there, a pretty way to be rid of Impertinent Iriſh Beggars.</p>
               <p>A certain <hi>Teaguelander</hi> came to ſome of his Comrades, and did ſay to them, <hi>who dear Joy, doe you think is dead, be Chreſt</hi> (ſays one) <hi>I cano tell,</hi> the other anſwered in the ſame manner, <hi>why faith, dear Joy, it is our Friend</hi> Mac Daniel, <hi>and au my ſhoul you muſt come to the Funerall,</hi> quoth the <hi>Teaguelanders</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rades, <hi>when did our Freind dye,</hi> quoth the Bog Trotter <hi>be did dye to Morrow be Chreſt,</hi> then quoth they, <hi>when will he be buryed,</hi> ſaid the other, <hi>he will be buried yeſterday, yes indeed, and ſo God reaſt his ſhoul.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>17</head>
               <p>One of St. <hi>Patrics</hi> Countrymen belonging to a certain Lord, did Enquire in <hi>Dublin</hi> in a certain Street for the Sign of the white Dog, to which he was anſwered, that there was no ſuch Sign as that, he goes a little further, <hi>War Joy,</hi> ſays the Teaguelander, <hi>canſt thou tell me where the white Dog is,</hi> no ſaid the Man, there is no ſuch Sign in this Street, <hi>be Chreſt,</hi> ſayes the other, <hi>it muſt be in this
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58213:23"/>Street;</hi> Then ſays the Man, there is the Talbott, but no white Dog, <hi>Po Po Po, Joy, be Chreſt that is the white Deg,</hi> ſays the Man I tell you no, it is the Talbot, ſaid the Teaguelander, <hi>Hold my dear Joy, you muſt not call it the</hi> Talbot, <hi>but the white Dog for the Lord Tyrconels's Name is</hi> Talbot, <hi>therefore you muſt ſay the white</hi> Dog.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>18</head>
               <p>A certain Lady ſending her Servant for ſome Candles, the Fellow meeting with a Comtade of his, ſtood talking in the Street with him, and having the Candles tyed up in a bunch he held then dangling in his hand, by and by comes a drunken Fellow along, and it hapned that this drunken Fellow beat the Candles out f his hand into the Dirt the Wealker being very durty, <hi>O</hi> ſaid the Teaguelander, <hi>be Chreſt I am undon my Lady will break my Pate and turn me away! O what ſhall I doe my Candles are all ſpoild in the Dirt;</hi> But the Candles had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived no further Prejudice then being dirty, ſayes <hi>Mac</hi> to his Country man, <hi>my dear Joy prethee tell me what I ſall doe to make my Candles clean and white as they were, for an my ſhoul I Care not goe home to my Lady till. I have made 'em clean;</hi> So laying their Noddles together, it was agreed by them both to goe to the next <hi>Coffee houſe,</hi> ſays Mac, <hi>Hark me dear Joy</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:58213:23"/>(to the Maſter) <hi>I faith I have had a great Misfortune, my Candles have fell in the dirt, and I dere not goe home to my Lady before they be clean, prethee Joy if thou canſt make 'em clean I ſall thank thee, and I will ſpend ſome mony in they houſe on my ſhoul I will, dear Joy;</hi> well ſaid the Coffee man, let me ſee them, the Coffee man took them &amp; put them into a Platter, and wash'd them with ſome of hot Liquor, ſo that the Dirt came off and ſome of the Tallow alſo, but they were clean; ſo the Coffee-man brought <hi>Mac</hi> the Candles; ſaid <hi>Mac, Noow be Chreeſt and de Devil tauke me, Y ſhware be him dat made me, thou baſt done dem very well, but on me ſhoul dear Joy, thou muſht dry them too, for dey be all vet,</hi> where shall I dry them (ſaid the Coffee man) <hi>Po po po, Joy, come hiſher wit me aund Y will ſhow dee,</hi> ſo he took the Candles and hung them in the Chimney; and he did ſay, <hi>Good Maſter Cooffeeman, predee geeve me a Pipe of Tobacco, Y vill ſmoak one Pipe, and be dat time dey vill be dree indede.</hi> While this Son of <hi>Teagueland</hi> was ſmoaking, the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles dript away all the while; ſo that when poor <hi>Mac</hi>'s Pipe was out, he did go for his Candles, but he could find none, then ſaid he, <hi>Be Chreeſt de damn Rogues hauve ſtole me Caundles! O me Shoul Y muſht not go home to me Laudy widout me Chaundles;</hi> but the Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feeman preſently show'd him the Wicks of his Candles, and told him the Tallow was all melted into the fire. This is an Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58213:24"/>how to dry Candles when they are wet.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>19.</head>
               <p>Another of the Sons of <hi>Teagueland</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving got into the Service of a worthy Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, and lying with the reſt of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants who did uſually fart; <hi>Mac</hi> told his Maſter of it, and ſaid to him, <hi>Dear Joy, predee mauke anoder Lodging, for I cano, lie vid de naſty Shervants;</hi> quoth the Maſter, what is the matter? quoth <hi>Mac, be Chreeſt dey de ſo fart and ſtink, dat O me ſhoul does, mauke me very ſhick:</hi> (quoth the Maſter) how can that make you ſick? <hi>Yeſh indede</hi> (quoth <hi>Mac</hi>) <hi>for be Chreeſt de ſtink of de Fart dos get into me Noſhe, ſhomtime into me Moutſh, and it goes doon into me Bally and dos mauke me full of de Gripe of de Gut, on me ſhalwaſhion it iſh true, and Y tauke me Snuſh, and be Chreeſt it all ſhmel of Fart:</hi> ſo his Maſter promiſed to remedy the matter for him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>20.</head>
               <p>another Son of <hi>Teagueland</hi> drinking Braudy with his Comrade, (ſaid to the other,) <hi>Dear Joy, we muſht not drink too muſh Braundy, it vill mauke uſh ſleep, and den we ſhall be deed, aſh me Friend waſh de oder day;</hi> ſays the other to him, <hi>How dead! I prethee how
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58213:24"/>doſt thou mean?</hi> the other replies, <hi>be Chreeſt Y bad a dear Friand did drink ſo muſh Brandy he did fall a ſleep, and be Chreeſt when he awaked be was deed, yeſh indede.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>21.</head>
               <p>A certain Nobleman having a Servant of <hi>Teagueland,</hi> whom he loved very well, and woud intruſt him with his Plate, and made him his Butler; this Fellow conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued honeſt a while, and having occaſion to drink with one of his Country men want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Money to entertain him abroad, having thought on ſeveral ways to get ſome, thoſe did not pleaſe him; at laſt he took one of his Maſters Diſhes, which was Silver, as his Lord us'd nothing elſe) and did find out a way to cut out his Maſter's Coat of Arms from the Plate, and threw the reſt down the Vault, becauſe it ſhould not be ſeen to accuſe him of his Theft; when he had ſo done, he and his Friend went to the Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, and having plentifully liquor'd themſelves: The aforeſaid Butler call'd to the people to change his money, and gave this piece to them, which was about the bigneſs of half a Crown; the people re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſns'd it, and ſaid it was none of the Kings Coyn; <hi>Be me Shoul, ſaid</hi> Mac. <hi>it iſh a vary guod haulf Croon, and Y vill go and chaunge it;</hi> ſo being near his Lords houſe, he went
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:58213:25"/>home and showed it to one of my Lords Gentlemen, and ſaid, <hi>Dear Joy, pradee geeve me two ſhallings aund ſixe pance for thiſh haulf Croown?</hi> the Gentleman anſwered, how Sirrah! this is my Lord Dukes Coat of Arms! <hi>Po, po, po, po, joy! O me Shoul dere iſh de King on horſheback; It iſh a very good haulf Croon;</hi> but the Lord Duke being acquainted of the paſſage, examined <hi>Mac</hi> where he had ht; <hi>be me Shoul,</hi> ſaid his Servant, <hi>Thou didſht put haulf Croons upon dy Plate, and Y had occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion for to mauke uſe of one with me Countryman, and Y did tauke it from dy Plate:</hi> The Lord ſaid, you Rogue, where is the reſt of the Plate; <hi>Po po, Joy, be Chreeſt dere iſh no more baulf Croons upon it, it iſh good for noting, O me ſhoul Y did fling de reſht in de houſe of Office;</hi> O Villain! ſaid the Nobleman, do you uſe theſe rogueries, I thought you very honeſt; <hi>O me ſhoul, dear Joy, be not aungry,</hi> ſays the <hi>Teaguelander, here iſh dy hauf Croon, and Y vill fetch dee de reſht of dy Plate if dou canſht mauke more baulf Croons upon it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>22.</head>
               <p>A certain Nobleman having one of theſe Macks to his Servant ſent him to his Drug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter for ſome <hi>Sarſaparilla</hi> (for his Lord did boil it with ſome other Ingredients, and drink it and as ſome drink <hi>Tea.</hi>) The Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant went to the Drugſters; and ſaid my
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:58213:25"/>Maſter muſt have ſome ſaucy Fellow <hi>from this Shop;</hi> the Maſter of the Shop ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined his Men, who of them had af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronted my Lord, that he ſhould ſend in this manner? but his Servants denied that they ever gave occaſion to my Lord to be angry. Whereupon the maſter going along with the Lords Servant to beg par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon or excuſe, if any thing had diſliked his Lordſhip; and as ſoon as his Man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, the Lord asked him for the <hi>Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaparilla?</hi> the Servant replyed, <hi>here is de Maſter of the Shop, Y have brought him wid me;</hi> You Rogue (quoth the Gentleman) I bid you bring ſome <hi>Sarſaparilla; be Chreeſt</hi> (ſays the Servant) <hi>dere is no ſaucy Fellow dere:</hi> At which both Lord and the Drug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter laughed heartily at the Ignorance of the Fellow; the Maſter returned home and ſent the <hi>Sarſaparilla</hi> by his Man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>23.</head>
               <p>Another Virtuoſo of <hi>Teagueland,</hi> being invited to a Veniſon Paſty, after he had fed very well, and ſatisfied himſelf; he came among his Friends and Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in the Evening, and as they were drinking, one begun to talk what a rare Dinner he had this day, and another
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:58213:26"/>told his Entertainment. At laſt the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuoſo that had din'd with the Paſty, ſaid, <hi>Be Chreeſt Y did dine with a Veniſon Paſty, it is true, but O my ſhoul! when it was firſt cut up, dere did come ſuch an Echo from it, was ready to ſtrike me down;</hi> ſome Moderns call it a Hogo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>24.</head>
               <p>Two certain <hi>Teaguelanders</hi> conſulted to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether how they might raiſe their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, and to get Money, one of them had obſerved ſome body burning of Gold and Silver Lace, and did intend to make a trial of them upon Guilded Leather, ſo he imparted this to his Comrade; <hi>Dear Joy, ſays he, you muſt aſſiſt me; dere is in ſuch a plauce, a room with Guilt Leather, we vill cut away the Guilt Leather and burn it, and in faith we vill be marry with de Money we mauke of it:</hi> They both put their reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution in practiſe, and did ſpoil a whole Room of that Furniture, and went away with it to have it burn'd: ſo they us'd an Alehouſe near their Maſters houſe, where they call'd for a Faggot and burnt it, and did put the Guilt Leather in the fire; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving drunk a Pot or two, by that time the Fire and Leather was conſumed, ſo
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:58213:26"/>they got a Broom and ſwept up Aſhes and all together, and then ſearched for the Gold that ſhould come from the Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; at laſt both of them being impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, having raked a pretty while, and could find nothing; the one ſaid to the other, <hi>be Chreeſt Y cano find de Gold, thou haſt ſtole the Gold:</hi> Says the other, <hi>O me ſhoul! dou art a lying Rogue, dou haſht rob'd me of me part and ſhtole it away:</hi> At theſe words they were hot at it, that at laſt with the Noiſe and fury of theſe <hi>Teague<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers,</hi> the Maſter came to part them, and enquire into the matter, and found they had been burning of Guilded Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to get the Gold from it, ſo he diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from whence they ſtole it, and the poor <hi>Teaguelanders</hi> had the gentle Laſh for it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>25</head>
               <p>A certain <hi>Teaguelander</hi> being upon his Journey, in his way chanced to light upon a ſmall Pig, ſayes he to the Pig, <hi>little Pig, will you come and ſtay with me a Moneth,</hi> the Pig did ſay, a week, a week, a week, a week, four times, <hi>then be Chreſt,</hi> ſayes Mac, <hi>that is a Moneth, for four Weekes mauke a month,</hi> but poor <hi>Teague</hi> was taken for ſtealing the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:58213:27"/>Pig, and carryed before a juſtice, and <hi>Mac</hi> did ſay, <hi>Mr. Juſtice, o my ſhalvation! the Pig did promiſe to live with me a Moneth, but if the Man will have him ſooner, here is the Pig for him.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>26</head>
               <p>Another of the ſame Country, hapned to the ſervice of a very honeſt Gentleman, who was much pleas'd with his Servants tallk, but his Maſter one time ſent him to receive forty pounds, and to bring it to him to ſuch a place, if he ſhould not be at home; Now <hi>Mac</hi> had been very juſt and faithfull in ſeverall Services his Maſter had em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd him in many times before, and his Maſter did not doubt him in this affair; however <hi>Mac</hi> goes according to his Maſters order and receives the forty pounds, poor <hi>Mac</hi> never ſaw the like before, and having the money, reſolv'd to run away with it to his own Country; But withall, he went home firſt to take ſome of his linen and other things with him which he was not willing to leave behind, little thinking to meet his Maſter there, when poor <hi>Mac</hi> came in to the houſe, the firſt he met with was his Maſter, ſays his Maſter, how now <hi>Mac,</hi> haſt thou received the Mony I ſent
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:58213:27"/>thee for? At which being ſurprized, <hi>Mac</hi> could not preſently anſwer, ſayes his Maſter, why dont you tell me Sirra whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you have received the mony? Quoth Mac, <hi>the Devill tauke thee and thy money too,</hi> quoth the Maſter, why ſo angry <hi>Mac?</hi> quoth Mac, <hi>A Plague tauke dee aund they money too, Y ſay, and there is they money, and the Devill tauke it;</hi> prethee why ſo angry? ſays the Maſter, ſayes Mac. <hi>be Chreeſt when Y had received they money the Decvill did tempt me to run away with it, yeſh indeed, but my Conſcience came behind me and fetch'd me back again, and ſo the Devill tanke thee and thy money to;</hi> Why <hi>Mac,</hi> where would you have run with it? quoth <hi>Mac, O my ſhoul! into mine own Country,</hi> in <hi>Mackland,</hi> then quoth the Maſter, I ſhould have fallow'd you thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and put you in Priſon, <hi>Po po po po, Joy, be Chreeſt if thou hadſt come there thou ſhouldſt have been my Man there.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>27.</head>
               <p>One <hi>Barnewell</hi> of <hi>Dunbrough</hi> in <hi>Teagueland,</hi> being a young Man, and his Father ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a very handſom Maid Servant in his Houſe, the Son had a great mind to lye with her, and upon a certain time when he went to the Prieſt to Confeſſion, amongſt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:58213:28"/>the reſt of his Sins, did Confeſs to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Fryer that he longed to lye with the Maid, but he never did attempt it; The Prieſt told him it was a great Sin never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, for ſaid the Prieſt, thou haſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted fornication in they heart, becauſe thou didſt luſt after her, and therefore thou muſt doe Pennance for this, for it is an Abomination; ſo the Prieſt enjoyn'd young <hi>Barnewell</hi> to go 30 miles to a certain Church, and there to Pray, and that he muſt goe and come back barefoot to Expiate his Crime: To which poor <hi>Barnewell</hi> was forced to doe becauſe he would not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oblige his own Father, but he was ſo gall'd and lam'd, and his feet ſo ſoar in the perſormance thereof, that he vow'd re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge upon the Prieſt; And it fell out, that upon a certain day a litle after his Penance, as <hi>Barnwell</hi> was looking about and Plowing ſome Ground which his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had gave him, he ſpy'd the Prieſt Mare looking into an Oat feild of his, but could not get to it, ſo <hi>Barnewell</hi> called his Man, and ſaid to him, <hi>doeſt thou not ſeerthe Prieſt Mare yonder looking into my Feild of Oats, be Chreeſt the Maure does luſt after my Oates, and Y will mauke the Maure doe Pennance for it;</hi> So <hi>Barnewell</hi> and his Man caught the Prieſts Mare, and opened an old ſtinking Pid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon-houſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:58213:28"/>door, and put the Mare in; The Prieſt the next day, having occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for his Mare, could not find her, and ſent all about to enquire after his Mare, but could hear no tidings; this continued about 5 days, the Prieſt then meeting with a Smith who as a Neighbour to <hi>Barnwell,</hi> ask'd him concerning his Mare; the Smith told him, he did belive <hi>Barnewell</hi> had play'd a ſtrick with the Mare, becauſe he vow'd (ſaid the Smith) to be revenged upon you for making him doe Pennance; Quoth the Prieſt, I have ſearch'd all about <hi>Barnewells</hi> Houſe and Ground, but I cannot find her, quoth the Smith to the Prieſt, Father, have you ſearched the Pidgeon-houſe? no <hi>be me ſhoul, ſaid the Prieſt;</hi> then the Smith and the Prieſt ſearched the Pidgeon-houſe and there found the Mare almoſt ſtarved and Chop-fall'n; The Prieſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained to <hi>Barnewells</hi> Father of his roguery, at which the old Man began to reprove his Son, and ſaid, thou great Rogue, why doeſt thou doe ſuch things to the Holy man; his Son anſwered him, <hi>on my ſhoul Father, he did mauke me doe Pennance becauſe Y did Confeſs to him I had a mind to lye with thy Maid, and he did tell me I did luſt after her, tho I did not lye with her, and by Chreeſt did mauke me go 30 miles harefoot, and my feet are
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:58213:29"/>ſoar to this day, and his Mare did luſt after my Oates, tho' he did not eat any, therefore I thought the Mare ſhould doe Pennance becauſe be did look and luſt aftn emy Corne?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>28.</head>
               <p>A great debate happened between a <hi>French</hi> Footman, and an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Footman, which of their Countries was moſt Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till; Quoth the Monſieur to the other, we have ſuch rich Graſs in <hi>Brittany, dat begar it vill grow over de Horſe Legs in won Night, begar: And be Shaint</hi> Holly-Head (replyed the other) <hi>vee have ſhuch fruitful Groundſh in</hi> Yrelandt, <hi>daat if dee mauke put in dy Horſhe into de Field at Neet, de caunſt not mauke find dy Horſhe in de Morning, in fait.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>29.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Will</hi> (who was Footman to Sr. <hi>Henry</hi>—) meeting with <hi>Mac,</hi> who was in the ſame quality with Eſq; <hi>F.</hi>— Says <hi>Will,</hi> how the pox didſt thou come by that broken Face <hi>Mac?</hi> haſt thou been in the Wars? or hath ſome Female ſcratcht thee? <hi>No be Shaint</hi> Antonie (<hi>replyed</hi> Mac,) <hi>Y vill tall dee indede, I did go and mauke dehauch wid ſhum of me Countrymans; aund whan Y did
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:58213:29"/>ſhee Y vaſh ſho dronke daat Y cou'd not go nor shtand, Y did run home ash fasht as Y cou'd drive indede, and be de Mash Y did faul a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shleep in de Shtreet by de vay, aund did mauke great Breake upon me Faush wid de fall, and de Vaatchmans did tauke me up, and caury me home indede.</hi> What in the Devil's name is all this (ſays <hi>Will?</hi>) thou cou'dſt not go nor ſtand, and yet didſt run home, and yet fell dead drunk in the way, and were carried home! why faith <hi>Mac,</hi> this is very aſtoniſhing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>30.</head>
               <p>A <hi>Dear Joy</hi> that had waited on a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman into <hi>Holland,</hi> told ſome of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rades, that the <hi>P.</hi> of <hi>O.</hi> lived at a very great and ſplendid rate, for that, <hi>Y hauve ſeen</hi> (quoth he) <hi>be Chreeſt, tree or four she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Courshes carried up to hish Tauble at vone Dinner, in fait, noow, la.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>31.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bryan</hi> having been ſent in an Errant to a Gentlemans houſe in the Country, fell deeply in Love with a <hi>Welch</hi> Maid, who belonged to the Kitching there, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time after he met a Footman belonging
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:58213:30"/>to the ſame Gentleman; <hi>Bryan</hi> deſired him to <hi>tauke</hi> a pot of <hi>drenk vid him, for a a quarter of an hour, vile he did mauke requeſt to shom Skriviſhner to vrite</hi> a Letter for him to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſula;</hi> which being done, <hi>be me shoul Y did pray him to shend it upon</hi> Urſula <hi>by do Vaaterman indede.</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Letter.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Shweet Mrs. <hi>Urſula,</hi>
                        </salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>BE de ham of me Moddarſh Smock, aund be aul de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſquebah daat vaſh drunk at mine Faderſh Vedding; de Dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil tauke me indede, but Y be ſho much in Lofe vid dee, daat Y cannot go to Bed aul the long Night for ſleeping upon dee; aund Y cannot be upon vaaking, but the Deevil tauke me, Y do fall upon dreaming conſharning
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:58213:30"/>thy ſhweet ſhelfe indede, daan do Y tink, vaat is the matre? vaat is the maatre vid mine awn ſhelfe? Aund Y do feend it is aal for much Love conſharning dee, in fait: Be me ſhalwaſhion Y vill tall dee vaat Y vill do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dede; Y vill put kiſh upon dy fauſh indede, and Y vill be for mauking Child upon dy Body indede, aund Y will mauke a great del more conſharning dee, dan dyne own Moddar in fait. Noow de Dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil tauke de faſhion, daat van two yong Cople of Man and Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man be for coming togadder vid on anodder, daat dare muſht be mauking upon the great She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimony of de Preſht, aund aul de People to mauke Witneſh upon
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:58213:31"/>it: Be me Shoul Y vill not manke ſtaying ſho long; but Y vill be dyne husband vidout aal daat now, aund be Shaint <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick,</hi> Ye vill love dee like auny ting indede. Y vill ſhend to <hi>Tredagh</hi> for mine Moddarſh tree Goats, four Sheep, one Filly Mare, and the tauny Coow, and vee will be for mauking a Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in <hi>Lincolns-Inn-Felds</hi> be Chreeſt, aund vee will mauke Butter and Cheſe, aund Eggs, and ſhell our ſhelves into Plauce and Conferrmant every day in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dede. And we vill ſhing Curds and Crame be Chreeſt, and But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar and Eggs, Bony-Clabber, and Tiff, untel de Coow ſhall have Caufe, de Maure ſhall have Colt,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:58213:31"/>de Goats ſhall have Kidd, aund <hi>Urſulah</hi> ſhall hauve Child in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dede; Aund dan vee vill ſhet up Houſh-kepin and be for livein aul togadder, be Chreeſt, as it is de faſhion in mine awn Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, in fait. Noow de Deevil tauke me, dear Joy, dou ſhaut be for ſending Aunſwer to vaat Y hauve ſent dee by de Skriviſhnar; aund if dee vilt mete me to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row morning at four of de Clock in de aufter noons, aut de Hole in de Vaal, vee vill go to Bed aund be Mawrry'd preſantly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dede, viddout de Charge of de Vedding, aund de Prieſts feſe be Chreeſt, aund vee vill put de grate Chete upon our Parantsh, aund be me Shoul vee vill be
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:58213:32"/>Mawrried, dear Joy; aund none body ſhaul be vyſher for it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dede; Aund being at ſuch dish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tansh daat Y cannot come to put Kiſh upon dy shweet faush, Y vill put a hondrad Kishes upon dish Pauper, and shend me Sharvish, aund me Affuction to dee indede, and me shalwashion Y vill alwash be</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Dine owne Dear Joy, <hi>BRYAN.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                     <postscript>
                        <p>Y have geeven de Vaaterman Shixpensh to breng it to dee, to shave de charge of de Penny-Posht in fait.</p>
                     </postscript>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:58213:32"/>
               <head>32.</head>
               <p>The Water-man was punctual, and put the Letter in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſulah</hi>'s own hand the ſame evening, telling her he had it from her <hi>ſweet heart,</hi> at which ſhe ſmiled like a <hi>furmity Kettle:</hi> when the Water-man was gon, ſhe ſhews her Letter to the <hi>Butler</hi> to read it for her her (but you muſt know) under an Obligation of ſecrecy; he may a ſhift to <hi>unriddle</hi> the <hi>marke</hi> at the bottom, but for the reſt, it was as unintelligible to him as the <hi>Original Welch,</hi> or the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptized Characters</hi> of <hi>Arabia:</hi> therefore they concluded it to be ſome very learned Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and it was agreed to deſire the <hi>Chaplain</hi> to read it; Sr <hi>John</hi> was almoſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell'd at the firſt ſight, but after ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration he made ſhift to <hi>Expound</hi> it, and to <hi>enlarge</hi> upon the <hi>Point:</hi> Telling the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience (who were compoſed of the Valet de Chamber, the Buttler, my Ladys wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man (whoe ought to have been named firſt) two Foot-men, the Coach-man, and three or four Servants of the Kitching;) That, though the Letter in it ſelf par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly conſidered, with reſpect to the <hi>Hand Maid</hi> therein mentioned, and to whome it did immediately relate, Savoured of nothing but a profound <hi>Love</hi> and ſincere <hi>Affection. (Looking meltigly, upon
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:58213:33"/>my Ladys Woman, and fetching a ſight;)</hi> Yet ſome <hi>paſſages</hi> therein contained, looked as black as the <hi>powder Plott;</hi> and carryed a deep <hi>Conſpiracy</hi> in them, and that againſt the whole Body of the <hi>National Clergy;</hi> which will prove worſe Madam (ſpeaking to my Ladys Woman) than a <hi>Telleration;</hi> &amp; it is plaine that the Atheiſtical part of men entertain theſe Varlets in perfect ſpleen to the <hi>Miniſtry.</hi> Wha to be robbed of their <hi>Comfertable Importance Fees? (Alas! Sr. ſays my Ladys Woman</hi> looking languiſhing upon the Chaplain) <hi>I ſay</hi> to be deptived of the ſweet and <hi>ſtanding Revenue, Entayled</hi> upon our <hi>Function,</hi> as long as People ſhall think fit to <hi>Copulate</hi> according to <hi>Modern Inſtituction:</hi> It is a <hi>I ſay</hi> it is a <hi>down right, Diametrical</hi> Contradiction to our <hi>Eſtabliſhment;</hi> which I will prove in nineteen, or twenty Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars humb! humb!</p>
               <p>Juſt as he was going to hold forth, the Gentleman of the Houſe came home, and (croſſing the Roome where this grave Aſſembly were) hey da (ſays he) what's here, a <hi>Conventicle?</hi> No a'nt pleaſe you Sr. (replyed my Ladys Woman) here is a'nt pleaſe you Sr. ſuch a diſcovery of a deſign upon Miniſtery, by a Letter from an <hi>Iriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> to one of the Kitching Maids, that if it be not prevented (a'nt pleaſe you) the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:58213:33"/>function will fall to the ground. Well ſaid Betty! (quoth the Gentleman) ſtanding up for the Clergy, or thon wilt loſe they <hi>Coppy hold.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Gentleman got into the Parler to his Lady, called for the Chaplain, and the Letter, which being read, he could hardly containe to hear the Comedy out; but that which mot pleaſed him was the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons <hi>Expoſition,</hi> and <hi>Notes</hi> thereon. Betty (allthe while) ſtood by my Ladys Chaire, touching, and whiſpering my Lady at every clauſe; Well Madam, this is a dangerous deſign againſt the Clergy, The Gentleman (being loth to loſe the further diverſion that might be Improved upon ſo Comical a <hi>Plot</hi>) bid the Chaplain provide to go with him to the City to morrow, and to have the Letter with him, and he would take care to ſee the <hi>Iriſh man</hi> taken to account for his deſign upon th eClergy, Sr. <hi>John</hi> was ſomwhat pacified with this; and in token thereof, tipt a winke upon Mrs. Betty.</p>
               <p>The next day the Gentleman met his Friend (the Maſter of (the Maſter of <hi>Bryand</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> and (at the <hi>Coffee-houſe</hi>) old him all the ſtory of his mans Letter, the Chaplains <hi>Notes</hi> thereon, and the ſport it had been to himſelf, and his Lady, and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:58213:34"/>that the Parſon and Letter were both in Town: His Friend replyed; he was much pleaſed at the Conceit of it; and that he would have him and the Chaplain dine at his houſe; The Gentleman accordingly ſent for his Chaplain, and they meet at his Friends at dinner. The love Letter was produced, and <hi>Bryan</hi> called <hi>coram Nobis;</hi> The Chaplain read the Indictment, by Explaining the Letter; And <hi>Bryan</hi> was examined upon the <hi>premiſes. Be Cheeſt</hi> (deare Joy) ſays he tome his Maſter; <q rend="inline">Now de Deevill tauke if diſh Prieſht be not de deevilliſh ſhon of a howr mauke all diſh Treaſhon upon me dan; vaat plotſh iſh it for me to tall de Maid vee will be marryed, ha! be ſhaint <hi>Pautrick</hi> it iſh ſhuch a damn Ting waare deſhe Parſhons doe come into he Houſe, dare iſh be not quiett in fait. Daare iſh ſometing beſhides daat maake me put Conſhideraſhion upon dee indede, aund daat iſh in fait to mauke hanging upon me indede, aund daan de vilt mauke Marriage upon mine ſhweet hart, mine Urſulah indede; Aund Y will mauke ſhware upon dee, daat dee vaſh ſhteal mine Lettre oout of of mine ſhoeet hartſh pocketſh; And dee vilt marry mine Urſhulah, aund put me upon mauke kill upon me ſhelfe for Love
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:58213:34"/>indede: Whoo! whoo! whoo! poo! Be ſhaint <hi>Pautrick</hi> Y will mauke petiſhion for dy plauſh noow, aund maake dee be put oout of dy Chaplainſh Comiſhion, aund dan Y will mauke ride avay vid all de Veemen mine awne ſhelfe be Creeſht, aund dee ſha't hang dy ſhelfe before Urſhula vill Love dee.</q> Some Strangers coming in to mauke a viſit, put a period to the reſt of the Comedie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>33.</head>
               <p>It was in <hi>Flanders</hi> that a certain <hi>Bog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lander,</hi> who was of the Army there; hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to be very much ſmitten with the Daughter of an Inhabitant at <hi>Bruſſelles:</hi> The young Gentlewoman was a zealous frequenter of Mattins, and Veſpers; where he had often opportunity to ſee-her, and Conſequently to be the more Captivated, but it was impoſſible for him to get ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance to her to make known the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of his paſſion, becauſe of the vaſt diſtance their difference Fortunes had put between them. He therefore made fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Oriſons, and was almoſt perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually rattling over his Beads, thumping his Breaſt, and uſing all the Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of a very fervent Devotion, in ſo
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:58213:35"/>much that a certain Boy that belonged to one of the Fathers had often Obſerved him to pay his Adorations to one parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ſhrine, and (by degrees) underſtood the <hi>buſineſs</hi> which put him upon thoſe fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Adreſſes. It was all for <hi>Love</hi> forſooth, it was the <hi>heat</hi> of his <hi>paſſion,</hi> that begat that of his <hi>Devotion:</hi> All his Applications were made to the figure of a Lady with a Child in her Arms; Whom he earneſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought to Incline the <hi>Idol</hi> of his thoughts to anſwer his Inclinations with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocal <hi>paſſion;</hi> And to be ſo propitious as to favour his Love with a fortunate minute, wherein he might diſcover the violence of that Irreſiſtable Flame, the Rayes of her Beauty had kindled in him, with abundance of ſuch Rhetorical Bum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſt which he had pickt (it's like) out of <hi>Wits Commonwealth,</hi> or the <hi>Accademy of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements;</hi> but ſtill accented and pronounced in the Tone of <hi>Dear Joy Land,</hi> interlarded with a world of <hi>O bone's! hoo! hoo! poo's,</hi> and the like; one wou'd have thought enough to have melted down a Lady of Marble. But tho it obtained not the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired effect, our Souldier knew not how to deſpair, but daily repeated his Addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and renewed his Vows to the Obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Shrine. The Boy before mentioned,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:58213:35"/>had one day placed himſelf behind the Statue, and that ſo advantageouſly, that the Souldier did not obſerve him; but with a <hi>Tone</hi> and <hi>geſture</hi> very <hi>pitiful,</hi> was heard to expreſs himſelf to this puppoſee</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deevil tauke me (dear Joy) Y hauve come a mauny timeſh indeed to mauke Shuplicauſhion to dee, and Y can nevar get one vord from dee in fait; now be his Holyneſh's Slipper, Y tinke it iſh vary hard indede date dee ſhouldſt uſhe a body after ſuch faſhion be Chreeſt; vaat poſht dee be in diſh plauce for, if de vilt not be ſho ſhivil to manke Aunſwer, vaan Y ſpeake to dee indede? daat Y do ſhay me hort is amoſht broke to peeſhes in fait, dare iſh no mauking belief in any body at all be Creeſt, aund dee beeſht ſho hord haurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, daat if Y do come to dee every day indede, dee vilt ſhay noting at aul to me in fait; Aund iſh not diſh very hord noow? Yeſh be ſhant</hi> Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick <hi>it iſh indede: Aund yet v'rall dat Y muſht be for coming to dee again, to mauke Shuplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions upon dee, daat Y may onderſhtand if ſhe vill be mauking Love upon me, or no be Chreeſt; aund if Y ſhaul make mauriage upon her indede?</hi> No, no, ſays the Boy behind the Picture, at which <hi>Dear Joy</hi> was in a very great diſcontent, and could hardly forbear ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into a fumigation; but a little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collecting, he proceeded: <hi>Noow Y prathee dear Joy, let that ſhame pratty little Child hold
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:58213:36"/>hiſh tongue, ſhpake to me vid dyne awn Lipſh indede; vaat doſht dee ſhay noow; ſhaul Y aver come to Bed to daat pratty Voman, daat Y vaſh ſpaking to dee aboout? aund upon me ſhalwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion indeed Y vill be for mauking Prayer to dee ſholong aſh Y live be Chreeſt:</hi> No, no, I ſay (ſays the Boy again) thou ſhalt never have her. <hi>Daan de deevil tauke me if aver Y do mauke Prayers upon dee any more be my Shoul, Y vill go aund mauke hang upon me ſhalf 'noow; aund de ſha't never ſhee me fauſh any more in fait noow, aund ſho fare dee vall dear Joy, indede.</hi> At which he marcht out of the Church in great Indignation, and the Boy was ready to burſt with the thought how he had impoſed upon poor <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lander.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A deare Joy being arraigned for ſtealing a Mare, and the Evidence making Oath they ſaw him lead her out of the Ground he was at length asked, what he could fay for himſelf? <hi>Now de Deevill tauke me it fait</hi> (ſays he) <hi>but heare iſh de greateſh parſhell of Lawyers daat ever vaſh in the World, vor upon me ſhalwaſhion</hi> (deare Joy) <hi>Y did but tauke de end of the bridle in fait, aund de Deevilliſh Jade came after indede, aund Y vaſh loat to cutt of de end of de Bridle, aund a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Chreeſht of dee doſht mauke haung upon it, dare well be au end of me Generaſhion indede, for
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:58213:36"/>me Vaadar, me Grandfar, me great Grandfar, and two Broddarſh waſh all hang'd for Shomti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſh after one anodder, ſhom vaſh for finding of Couſh, ſhom for Sheepſh, aund ſhom for mauking Murder be Creeſht, aund de Deevil tauke de envanſhion of hampe in fait, for iſh mauke deſtruſhion upon aull me vaadarſh Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily indede. And be ſhaint Pautrick if dee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſht mauke putting the haang upon me, Y vill navar mauke forgett of it indede, La.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
